<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration against a crosse petition: wherein some secret lets of the intended reformation are discovered. The danger of division prevented. And the unity of this iland in religion urged. By the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E89_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21173</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99870435</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99870435</idno>
            <idno type="VID">122828</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82032)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 122828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 15:E89[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration against a crosse petition: wherein some secret lets of the intended reformation are discovered. The danger of division prevented. And the unity of this iland in religion urged. By the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>First, printed at Edenburgh, and now reprinted at London for I.B. in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642 [i.e. 1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Originally published: Edenburgh, 1642?.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb [illegible]".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  History, (17th century)</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:122828:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION AGAINST A CROSSE PETITION: WHEREIN <hi>Some ſecret lets of the intended reformation are diſcovered. The danger of Diviſion prevented. And the unity of this Iland in religion urged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY THE COMMISSIONERS OF THE GENERALL ASSEMBLY.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Printed at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and now reprinted at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>I. B.</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:122828:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:122828:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Word of GOD, the example of the People of GOD, and of the Kirk of Chriſt, ſince the beginning, and our own late, but very notable and never to be forgotten experience, may abundantly teach us, that the motions, reſolutions and endeavours of the Godly, for the advancement of the Kingdome of the Son of GOD, by eſtabliſhing or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating the Reformation of Religion, muſt meet with a world of oppoſition and hinderances, which might make their hearts to faint, and their hands to faile, if upon the ſame grounds and documents they were not taught to acquit themſelues, in doing the duty required of them by the neceſſity of their callings, and for the ſucceſſe to depend upon the unſearchable wiſedome, and invincible power of GOD, which are made perfect in the ſimplicity and weakneſſe of his ſervants: <hi>The zeale of the Lord of hoſts will performe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There hath ever been in the Kirk of Chriſt, and ſhall be to the end, a generation which maketh more account of the World, then of the Faith of Chriſt, doth conceive that differences about Religion are but the contentions of Kirk-men, that therefore there is no neceſſity of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion, and that to know nothing of this kind, is the ſureſt Faith, and ſeeketh in their ſervice to Kings and Princes civilly to ſupererogate at their hands, beyond the deſervings others, and above the expreſſed deſires and commands of Princes themſelves, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of their ſingular zeale may be the greater, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have proven, and daily do prove the moſt pernicious and dangerous enemies of the true Religion: againſt this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:122828:3"/>generation, which ſaith, <hi>Let us deale wiſely with them,</hi> we have this comfort and advantage, and we know amongſt all the Enemies of the Truth, they leaſt of all thinke that they doe God ſervice.</p>
            <p>We who are intruſted for the time, to be the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the late Generall Aſſembly, ſitting at <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> for the Affaires of the Kirk committed to our care and diligence, ſpecially for preſerving of our owne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and peace againſt all ſorts of Enemies, and according to the intereſt of this Kirk for unity in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Uniformity of Government with the Kirk of <hi>England,</hi> which was no new motion of ours, but a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition made by the Commiſſioners of the Treaty, which then received from the Kings Majeſty and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England,</hi> ſuch an Anſwer as hath beene the ground of many Conſultations, Declarations, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Letters ſince, and of a renewed ſupplication at this time to the Kings Majeſty, and of a Declaration to the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> for the ſame effect. While wee are thus exerciſed, we are deſired by ſome Noblemen, Barons, and Burgeſſes, occaſionally met at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to ſend ſome of our number to joyne with them in a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, repreſenting to the Right Honourable the Lords and other Commiſſioners of Parliament for the conſervation of peace, their humble thoughts and feares that the print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of His Majeſties Letter of the date, <hi>December</hi> 5. by Warrant and Command of the Right Honourable the Lords of His Majeſties Privy Councell, and the not printing of the Declaration of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unto which the printed Letter was an Anſwer, might be taken by the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> as an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the whole matter, and all the particulars which it did expreſſe, and thereby to animate and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke this Nation againſt them as Rebels and Traitours
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:122828:3"/>We finding that the Petition did homologate both in the end and meanes with our Commiſſion, and the matter of our preſent deliberations did willingly ſatisfie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the Petitioners, and therefore from our tender and dutifull reſpect to His Majeſties Honour, for preventing and removing of all occaſion of jealouſies and ſuſpitions betwixt the two Kingdomes, for preſervation both of our owne peace at home, and our common peace with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and for promoving the ſo much deſired Unity of Religion, a meane of all other moſt conducing to the conſervation of both, did with them (conforme to the order obſerved in ſuch caſes ſince the beginning of our late Reformation) humbly ſupplicate, that the meaning of the publication of his Majeſties Letter might be clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and that the Declaration of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to their Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> might be printed and publiſhed, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But behold, after a few daies a contrary Petition is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Lords of His Majeſties Privie Councell, by ſome private Noblemen, Barons, and Gentlemen, which comming to our hands, we found after due examination to be nothing elſe but a ſecret plot and ſubtle under-mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all the preſent deſignes of this Kirk and Kingdom, for Unity of Religion, and of all the work of God in this Land: And therefore we made upon it the Obſervations and Animadverſions following.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The private perſons knowing that the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Generall Aſſemblie were ſitting at this time about ſuch matters as they meddle with in their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that we had joyned in preſenting a Petition to the Commiſſioners for conſerving of Peace, much about the ſame particulars, whereof they could not be ignorant by reaſon of the Act of the late Aſſembly, they did not ſo much as acquaint us with their intentions, that we might
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:122828:4"/>either have petitioned with them, or have adviſed them to deſiſt: which although it may ſeem to be but an erro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the manner of their doing, yet doth it imply contempt, uſurpation and diviſion; and being winked at may be the cauſe of much diſturbance and confuſion in theſe times, eſpecially they profeſſing that they deſire to cleare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their intentions, not onely to the Lords of Councell, but to the Kings Majeſty, to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> and to all the World, which is nothing elſe but under the colour of a Petition to make a publique Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, contrary to the proceedings, not onely of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly and their Commiſſioners, but alſo to the deſires and diligence of the Commiſſioners of the Treaty of the Honourable Lords of Councell, and of the Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators of Peace, who have all concurred, and doe ſtill concurre in their joynt deſires of Unity of Religion in His Majeſties Dominions, reſolving to preſſe this Unity to the uttermoſt of their endeavours as a neceſſary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative of our own Reformation and Peace, which without it cannot long ſubſiſt; and much croſſing that clauſe of our Covenant wherein we ſweare, that we ſhall not caſt in any let or impediment that may ſtay or hinder any ſuch reſolution, as by common conſent ſhall be found to conduce for ſo good ends.</p>
            <p>Although the Petitioners profeſſe with us that they deſire the Union of this Iland in Religion and Kirk-Government, yet their Petition doth too plainely and palpably tend to the contrary, as is apparent by this three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold conſideration: 1. For remedy of the diviſions and diſtractions in <hi>England,</hi> the Petition deſireth onely <hi>the ſuppreſſion of inſolent Papiſts, malignant ſchiſmatickes, and diſloyall Browniſts and Separatiſts, the ſpeciall, if not ſole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movers and fomenters of theſe unhappy miſ-underſtandings:</hi> and thus doth paſſe by the Prelates, and balketh the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:122828:4"/>Biſhops, who have bin the moſt reſtleſſe ſticklers in this buſineſſe, and the prime authors of all theſe tragedies ſince the beginning, and thereby would take us off our right and ſtraight courſe of preſſing uniformitie in Kirk-government, in the Treatie, in our Declarations, and in the Generall Aſſembly: The Apologiſts for the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would have reduced the Prelates either to Papiſts, or to Sectaries; but the Authors of the Petition intended better ſervice, by ſending the Petition to England, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trenching upon the Lordly Prelacy, or touching the Prelates at all; which from ſtrangers is an high provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Kingdome and Parliament of England, and no ſmall prejudice againſt the proceedings of this Kirk and Kingdome for Reformation. 2 This Petition doth indirectly caſt foule aſpertions upon thoſe who are moſt zealous for the reformation in England, and doth very much ſymbolize with the language of the Popiſh and Prelaticall party in England; calling the Parliament, and all that ſeek after Reformation, <hi>Browniſts, Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Authors of tumultuary conventions,</hi> &amp;c. 3 It hint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at our zeal and forwardneſſe in the matter of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Kirk of England: which may appeare thus; The Petitioners declare, <hi>That ſince the duty of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity doth oblige all Chriſtians to pray and profeſſe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, that all others were of the ſame Religion with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> etc. Therefore they repreſent their wiſhes for uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Religion and Kirk-government, as an expreſſion and teſtimonie of their affection to the good of their brethren in England: Declaring further, That <hi>they deſire this work to be proſecuted without preſuming or uſurping to preſcribe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wes and rules of Reformation to their Neighbours.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain they repeat, that <hi>by their wiſhes and deſires they intend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o wayes to paſſe their bounds, in preſcribing or ſetting downe rules and limits to his Majeſtie and Houſes of Parliament
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:122828:5"/>their wiſdome and authoritie, in the way of proſecution hereof.</hi> And why do they ſo plentifull purge, and carefully cleare themſelves concerning this particular, if their intention were not to leave ſome aſperſion upon this Kirk and State, as if we were paſſing our bounds, by preſuming to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe rules and limits to His Majeſty and Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament? For further evidence whereof, it is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that in the firſt part of their Petition they plainly profeſſe, that they are clearing themſelves and their intentions, leſt they ſhould be thought to be invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with us in the ſame deſires, judgements, and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: So that all which they ſay by way of clearing of themſelves and their intentions, ariſeth from this ground, that they will not be thought involved with us in our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, Judgements, and opinions, and ſo condemne us in theſe particulars in which chiefly they juſtifie themſelves: neither can wee knit together their words, or interpret their apologie to another meaning. Now what is this elſe but to overturne the very foundation of all our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for this work of Reformation, which was the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Treatie for union in Religion, and uniformity in Kirk government? Not as a matter nakedly deſired and wiſhed for, but as a principall demand, and neceſſary mean, without which neither truth nor peace could be ſecured unto us. The importance and neceſſitie whereof hath bin ſince that time ſo deeply laid to heart by this Kirk and Kingdome, that as the Generall Aſſembly, and we for our part repreſenting the ſame, ſo the Lords of Counſell, and the Commiſſioners of Parliament for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the peace, concurring with us, have been, and are moſt ſerious and ſolicitous in the importunate and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt preſſing of this union in Religion and Kirk govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reſolving to uſe our uttermoſt endeavours in the proſecuting and effectuating of ſuch a bleſſed and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:122828:5"/>neceſſary work, as being dearer to us then all our lives and Fortunes: neither did the Generall Aſſembly ſpare to repreſent their humble advice concerning the way of proſecuting that work to the Houſes of Parliament, and to others ſeeking after Reformation in England.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Their Petition doth tend to a dangerous diviſion in this Kirk and Kingdom; for as it doth reflect upon us for our joyning in the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning His Majeſties printed Letter preſented to the Com. of Parliament, for conſervation of the Peace, upon a pretext (as it ſaith) of the not ſitting of the Privy Councell at that time; ſo it inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuateth, that we did preſume to queſtion or ſeek of the Lords of Councell an account of their Actions; both which are foule and groundleſſe aſperſions: yea, it declareth, that the Petitioners do ſo far diſlike our Petition, that they conceive they were wanting in their dutie and allegeance to the Kings Majeſtie, if by their ſilence they ſhould ſuffer themſelves to be involved with us in the like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, judgements and opinions: thus plainly profeſſing a diviſion and ſeparation, aſwell from us, as from other Noblemen, Gentlemen, Burgeſſes, and Miniſters, here occaſionally met, with whom we joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the foreſaid Petition. And not content to withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from being involved with us, the Petition doth alſo inſinuate, that in their opinion we are involved in the breach of dutie and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance to the Kings Majeſtie; and not we onely, but the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners for conſerving the Peace, who did hearken and aſſent to our Petition, and did ſeriouſly recommend to the Lords of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Privie Councell, that part of the Petition which did concerne their Lordſhips clearing of their meaning in the publication of His Majeſties Letter, by their cauſing print the Declaration of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England. The Lords of Councell are likewiſe involved in the ſame breach of allegeance, by reaſon of their grant of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in cauſing print the Declaration of both Houſes of Parliament, upon the warrant of another Letter from His Majeſtie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with declaring, that their Lordſhips publication of any Paper, doth not import their approbation of the contents thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> The Petition above-mentioned doth import no ſmall prejudice to the happie Union and late Treaty of Peace betwixt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, inſinuating to the Lords of His Majeſties Privie Councell, that their Lordſhips in anſwering our Petition concerning the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their meaning in the publication of His Majeſties Letter,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:122828:6"/>might do no act which might give His Majeſtie occaſion to repent him of that truſt for aid and aſſiſtance, which He was pleaſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in his Letter December 5. that he repoſeth in us His Subjects of this His ancient and native Kingdom; whereby the Petitioners do in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mate their deſires, that the Lords of Councell might not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that for which we did ſupplicate, but to declare by their not printing the Declaration of the Parliament, that their Lordſhips publication of His Majeſties Letter did import their approbation of the contents thereof, and ſo acknowledge their willingneſſe to take Arms againſt the Parliament of England, upon the grounds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in that Letter, when His Majeſty ſhall require them ſo to do. And for their own part they declare, that they think themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged <hi>in every cauſe which may concern His Majeſties honour to concurre with their friends and followers in quiet manner, or in Arms, as they ſhall be required of His Majeſtie, his Councell, or any having his authoritie.</hi> Which if underſtood and applyed aright, no loyall Subject can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but it is meant and expreſſed in their Petition, as in oppoſition to our Petition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So in contemplation of the Differences betwixt His Majeſtie, and the Parliament of England, unto which their words relate. For they profeſſe to repreſent ſuch particulars as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident will much conduce to the removing of all the miſtakes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt His Majeſtie, and the Parliament: of which particulars, that is the firſt, That according to His Majeſties truſt expreſſed in His Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter December 5. the Subjects of this Kingdom declare themſelves willing and ready to take Arms in every cauſe which may concerne His Majeſties honour, being required by His Majeſtie, or any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving His Authoritie. And is not this to make void the Treaty, rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the publick Faith of this Kingdom, and Act of Parliament, diſcharging all taking up of Arms againſt the Kingdom or Subjects of England, upon any pretence whatſoever, without conſent of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, declaring the breach of Peace; and that after three moneths warning? Which treaty the Eſtates of Parliament did ſweare to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve inviolably, in the ſame very oath in which they did ſwear al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance to the Kings Majeſtie; thereby declaring, that the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the concluſions of the treaty may well conſiſt with our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and allegeance to our Soveraigne, whereas the Petition doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly put ſome aſperſion of Laeſmajeſtie upon the Parliament for confirming and ſwearing to obſerve the Articles of the Treatie,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:122828:6"/>which in the opinion of the Petitioners are conſiſtent with our oath of allegeance. If they ſay that their Petition did onely inſinuate that we may not take Arms to aſſiſt the Parliament againſt the King, they put upon it a ſenſe which it cannot be ar, both becauſe they knew that the ſupplication of the Noblemen, Barons, &amp; others aſſiſted by us, did not directly nor indirectly contain any ſuch thing, And becauſe His Majeſties truſt expreſſed in that Letter (which they deſire His Majeſtie may not have occaſion from us to repent) is not onely a negative truſt, that we will not take arms againſt him, but a poſitive truſt and confidence, that we will be readie to aſſiſt him. And finally, becauſe the clauſe of the Supplication of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Aſſembly which they mention as containing our obligation to our Soveraigne, and that in reference to the preſent diſtractions in England, is poſitive, and not negative.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Laſtly, the Petitioners for their own private ends doe very much wreſt and miſ-apply our Nationall Covenant, about which the whole Nation, and all the Members of the Kirk of Scotland have as great iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as by the mind of man can be conceived, to be moſt tender and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telous; and which every one amongſt us, according to his place and calling, is obliged to vindicate from every violation; and namely, from ſiniſter gloſſes, and falſe interpretations, which may be the fountaine and cauſe (the Covenant being one principall rule of our actions and undertakings) of many ſcruples, tranſgreſſions, and diſturbances. Wee acknowledge before God, and profeſſe before the World, that by our Covenant we are bound to the utmoſt of our power, with our meanes and lives, to ſtand to the defence of our dread Soveraigne the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, his Perſon and Authoritie, in the defence and preſervation of the true Religion, Lawes and Liberties of this Kirk and Kingdome; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in every cauſe which may concerne his Majeſties honour, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lawes of this Kingdome, and the duty of good Subjects, to concurre with our friends and followers in quiet manner, and in arms, as we ſhall be required of His Majeſtie, his Councell, or any having his authoritie. We know, that he who wilfully tranſgreſſeth one Article of the Covenant, it being copulative, is by interpretation guiltie of all. And therefore under the greateſt paines expreſſed in the Covenant, we reſolve for our ſelves, all the dayes of our lives, and doe exhort, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to that duty which they have ſworne and ſubſcribed to performe to the Kings Majeſtie: But we deſire to know of the Petitioners, who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:122828:7"/>are ſo ready at this time to make their own concluſions out of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which was never intended by it, nor thought upon at the firſt or laſt time at the ſwearing and ſubſcribing thereof, how it commeth to paſſe that they never took the Covenant in their mouth, but in this one Article? Are they not bound by their Covenant, and the ſame clauſe of the ſupplication, cited by them, to their mutuall concurrence and aſſiſtance for the cauſe of Religion? and to ſtand, with their means and lives, to the defence thereof, in the doctrine and diſcipline of the Kirk of Scotland? and to live godly, ſoberly, and righteouſly in this preſent world? True Conſcience of duty and ſincerity in keeping the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, will make the obedience univerſall. Secondly, ſeeing the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners would onely have unitie in Religion, and uniformitie in Kirk-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment advanced by Chriſtian wiſhes and faire meanes, and yet inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuateth their offer by armes to decide the municipall debates of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> anent Civill matters, while the Civill and Eccleſiaſtick Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the reſt of this Kirk and Kingdome are deſiring an Aſſembly, and a Parliament, to conſider their intereſt and duty, and to contribute their beſt endeavours (in what is above the power of their Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) to further this unitie of Religion, and remove theſe diſtractions in <hi>England,</hi> we aske, whether they preſume that they alone keepe the Covenant, and would render unto Chriſt which is Chriſts, and unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> which is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> and that all others are Covenant-breakers? Thirdly, doe they not know that the Covenant was ſubſcribed in the years, 1581. and 1591. before King <hi>James</hi> was King of <hi>England?</hi> and that in the particular Heads and Articles, it is qualified by expreſſe limitations and reſtrictions to this <hi>Kirk and Kingdome, to the Religion, Lawes and Liberties of Scotland?</hi> therefore can no more be extended to municipall debates, and to the Lawes and Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> unto which we are ſtrangers, then the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> can judge of our Lawes, and determine our differences, the two Kingdomes being ſtill independent, and not ſubordinate one to another, but parallell, which is more at large expreſſed in the beginning of the treaty of Peace: Nor is the ſending of our Forces into <hi>Ireland</hi> a neceſſary duty of our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but a voluntary teſtimony of our high reſpects to our King, and of our brotherly kindneſſe to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> as was expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Eſtates in the laſt Parliament. Fourthly, doe not the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners obſerve the limitations expreſly contained in the words cited by themſelves, <hi>according to the Lawes of this Kingdome, and duty of good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects?</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:122828:7"/>which ſome of them may remember was interpreted in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, as if it had been ſaid within this Kingdome; nor was there ever any law of this Kingdom of further extent: A law and Treaty there is, we know, ſorbidding it. Fifty, may they not learne from the printed Letter, that the Kings Majeſtie expreſſeth not his confidence of aſſiſtance from <hi>Scotland,</hi> upon any ground or article of the Covenant, which his Majeſtie knoweth to be ſo obligatory among us, but from the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, duty and affection of His Subjects of Scotland, without any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Covenant? But ſuch is the ſupererogation of ſome of the Petitioners above what His Majeſtie requires, that they will put a tye of the Covenant upon us, where GOD and the King hath leſt us free. Thus have we related the interpretation of the Covenant made by the Aſſembly, and vindicate that clauſe of the Covenant, which is ſo farre perverted by this Petition.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners hearing that their Petition had given offence to the Commiſſioners of the Aſſembly, and that we were about the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination and cenſuring thereof, did direct foure of their number with another Petition to give ſatisfaction to the exceptions that might be taken againſt them, as is contained in their Remonſtrance which they exhibite for that end: But when in a calme and quiet conference, al the particular reaſons above-written, were repreſented unto them, and all meanes uſed to move them to part from their Petition, they could not be induced, neither in the name of others that had ſent them, nor for themſelves, to acknowledge the ſmalleſt errour either in the matter of their Petition, or in the manner of their petitioning; only they made offor to joyne with us the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the Aſſembly in a new Petition for Unitie of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and gave ſuch gloſſes and interpretations upon the clauſes of their Petition, which were moſt excepted againſt, as could neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with the words nor ſcope of the contrivers and authors. And therefore being deſired and carneſtly dealt with, they not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to declare under their hands that no other thing was meant in the Petition, then they had by word expreſſed, but alſo did ſhun to allow or permit us, the Commiſſioners of the Aſſembly, to declare ſo much in their names, as was contained in their own verball ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, intending that the Petition ſhould go through this and the neighbouring Kingdomes for the ends for which it was deviſed, and eſpecially into England, for fruſtrating all that hath been done,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:122828:8"/>or is now in doing by this Kirk and Kingdome, out of their pious intention, and by their publick endeavours for Unitie of Religion, and the Peace of the two Kingdomes: And in the mean time that nothing ſhould be extant from them or their confeſſions and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations in the contrary.</p>
            <p>In this caſe we Judge it neceſſary, and find it incumbent to us to emit this Declaration, for vindicating our preſent and by-paſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings: For our ſilence and connivence were a breach of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to GOD, a neglect of the charge and truſt committed unto us by the Generall Aſſembly, an occaſion as well of diviſions at home, as of jealouſies and miſ-underſtandings betwixt the Kingdomes, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Petitioners in their errour, and an indirect approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Petition; as likewiſe a cauſe of ſtumbling and doubting to others who ſhall read or heare of ſuch a Petition, eſpecially to thoſe, who through want of diſcerning, are not able to prove things that are different, might be eaſily deceived by their pretexts and ſophiſtications. We are not ignorant that this Petition doth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much reflect upon the Parliament, Privy Councell, and the Conſervators of Peace; but this we leave to the wiſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe civill Judicatories, as they ſhall finde themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned: We have contained our ſelves within our proper Spheare, not daring to neglect our own duty, while wee forbeare to meddle with that which pertaines to others.</p>
            <p>The Petitioners are not all of one kinde and diſpoſition of heart, but are unequally voked againſt the Worke of God. Some of them are knowne, and ſome of them have been conceived to bee Maglig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Incendiares from the beginning: but God forbid that they ſhould now by oppoſing untie in Religion and Peace, prove ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to all Religion and Righteouſneſſe; for then will it bee both thought and ſpoken, that all this time paſt they have been lying in wait for the ſeaſon, when their malignancie might appear; and it will be obſerved, that they who were of late at diſtance amongſt themſelves, are now at agreement; and that like <hi>Samſons</hi> ſoxe, they turne taile to taille with fire-brands in the midſt, to burne up the husbandrie of GOD, when now the fields are white for the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt. It cannot be the cauſe of God which is not either ſecretly or openly oppoſed by men of perverſe minds; nor can blinded minds and hardned hearts till God touch them by his power, chooſe but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:122828:8"/>ſecretly or openly oppoſe the truth and cauſe of God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is very neceſſary that ſuch men take heed unto themſelves, leaſt by their fulneſſe of all ſubtletie and miſchiefe, and their not cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to pervert the right wayes of the Lord, they bee found to bee fighting againſt God which will prove bitterneſſe in the end: Others there be who have joyned in this Petition (to judge charitably) not from oppoſition to the unitie of Religion, they having done and ſuffered ſo much, and hazarded all for the Reformation of Religion at home, but partly out of unwillingneſſe to refuſe or diſpleaſe their friends to whom they are obliged by naturall or other particular bands and partly by reaſon of the ſpecious pretences in the Petition, not conſidering the bad intentions of the contrivers, or the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous importance and conſequence of the Petition it ſelfe: Let ſuch men, to whom the Commiſſioners of the Aſſembly wiſh all true happineſſe, ſeriouſly thinke as well upon the condition of the worke, and the quallitie of the company with whom they joyne, as upon their owne intentions, leaſt they wrong both themſelves, and the cauſe of God, contrary to their deſires, and more then they are aware of; and let them remember how dangerous it is to walke in the counſell of the ungodly, for their ſoules to come into their ſecret, and their glory to be joynd with that Aſſembly If counſell be like the principall agent, conſent is like the inſtrument; and to be inſtruments of, or acceſſorie unto the hindrance of the intended, and ſo much deſired unitie of Religion, which maketh ſo fair a way for the Kingdome of Chriſt through the earth, how great a ſin is it? and how great a ſorrow ſhall it be?</p>
            <p>All this we have thought good to expreſſe concerning that diviſive Petition, and thoſe who are joyned together in it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt in our way as a ſtumbling block and rock of offence, for hinderance of the work of God, both at home and abroad. And as Wee exhort and warne all the people of God in this Land to obſerve them who cauſe diviſions and offences, and to avoid them; So we hope aſſuredly, that no ſuch courſes, nor counſels ſhall proſper, as do tend directly or indirectly, to the ſtopping of the courſe of the Goſpell, or to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Religion and Reformation, and that God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:122828:9"/>ſhall againſt al impediments carry forward this his bleſſed and glorious Work, to the glory of his great Name, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Kingdom of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Antichriſt, to the firme Peace and happy Union of all His Majeſties Dominions in Religion, and to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Honour and Happineſſe: Whom GOD preſerve to raign long and proſperouſly over us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <head>At <hi>Edenburgh</hi> the <hi>18,</hi> day of <hi>Ianuary, 1643.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Commisſioners appointed by the Kings Majeſtie, and his Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for conſerving the Articles of the Treaty, Doe finde that the Petition given in to His Majeſties Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Councell by ſome Noblemen and Gentlemen upon the tenth of this <hi>Moneth,</hi> doth tend to the hindrance of their proceedings and endeavours, in this publik <hi>Work</hi> committed to them by the Kings Majeſtie, and Parliament: And that it is prejudiciall to the authority of this <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> the ſame being in oppoſition of what was that day recommended by the ſaid <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> to the Councell. And ordaine this <hi>Act</hi> to be publiſhed for ſtopping all farther progreſſe of that or other Petitions of that kind, And that it be Printed with the Declaration of the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of the <hi>Generall Aſſembly</hi> made here anent.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sic ſubſcribitur <hi>Arch. Primeroſe</hi> Cler. Commiſſ.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
